Register of the Ed Clark papers, 1972-1994
Hoover Institution Archives
Ed Clark papers
1972-1994
2002C2
Clark, Ed, 1930-
12 manuscript boxes, 1 card file box, 1 film reel (5.26 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection includes correspondence, speeches and writings, press releases, clippings, election campaign literature, polling data, minutes, financial records, video tapes, sound recordings, and photographs related to Libertarian Party electoral activity, especially in the presidential election of 1980.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Williamson Evers papers, Hoover Institution Archives
June R. Genis papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Karl Peterjohn papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Lawrence Samuels collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
1930 May 4 Born, Middleboro, Massachusetts
1952 B.A. in international relations, Dartmouth College
1952-1954 Lieutenant (junior grade), gunnery officer and destroyer escort, United States Navy
1954-1965 Lieutenant, United States Naval Reserve
1957 Graduated from Harvard Law School
1970 Married Alicia Garcia Cobos
1972- Founding state chair of the Libertarian Party of New York State
1972-1974 Vice chair, Libertarian Party
1972-1978 Member, National Committee, Libertarian Party
1974, circa Elected state chair of the Libertarian Party of California
1974- Attorney for Atlantic Richfield Company (ARCO), specializing in anti-trust law
1977 Elected to area governing council of the Health Systems Agency in Los Angeles County
1978 Candidate for governor of California, nominated by the Libertarian Party of California
1980 Candidate for president of the United States on the Libertarian ticket
2000 Received Thomas Jefferson Award from Libertarian Party
Scope and Content of Collection
Ed Clark was the Libertarian Party candidate for governor of California in 1978 and for president of the United States in 1980. His papers, which predominately document these two campaigns, include correspondence, speeches and writings, press releases, clippings, election campaign literature, polling data, minutes, financial records, video tapes, sound recordings, and photographs.
In his gubernatorial campaign, Clark received more than 5 percent of the popular vote. Although he campaigned as a Libertarian candidate and was the nominee of the Libertarian Party of California, Clark appeared on the ballot as an independent candidate. Important issues in his campaign included education, taxes, and job growth. He supported Proposition 13, which sought to limit property taxation, and campaigned against Proposition 6, also known as the Briggs Initiative, a proposition that would have limited gay and lesbian rights. The California gubernatorial campaign of 1978 file, which documents Clark's campaign, includes his correspondence and statements on issues.
In 1980, Clark campaigned for president of the United States as the Libertarian Party candidate. He appeared on the ballot in all fifty states and received more than 1 percent of the popular vote. In his campaign, Clark argued for curbing inflation, reducing taxes, and providing tax credits for education. He supported a non-interventionist foreign policy and opposed the draft and energy subsidies. The campaign ran national television advertisements that were largely funded by Clark's running mate, David Koch. The United States presidential campaign of 1980 file includes a clippings scrapbook covering Clark's campaign; correspondence between Clark and David Nolan, who was the founder of the Libertarian Party; and files of Alicia Clark, who campaigned for her husband, Ed Clark. The Audiovisual material includes a sound recording of Clark's speech upon accepting the presidential nomination as the candidate for the Libertarian Party, as well as other sound recordings and films related to his presidential campaign.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Libertarian Party.; Libertarianism--United States.; Presidents--United States--Election--1980.; Free enterprise.; Videotapes; Phonotapes
Collection Contents
- California gubernatorial campaign of 1978 file, 1972-1981 (Box 1-2)
  Includes correspondence, speeches, and printed matter related to Clark's campaign for governor of California. Arranged alphabetically by format.
  - Buttons, circa 1978 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Correspondence (Folder 1)
    - General, 1978-1979 (Folder 1: 2-5)
      Includes post-election correspondence
    - Koch, Charles, 1978 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Forms (Folder 1)
    - Form 720: statement of economic interests, 1977-1978 (Folder 1: 7)
      Includes instruction manual
    - Nomination forms for independent candidate, 1978 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Libertarian Party News newspapers, 1978 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Pamphlets, circa 1978 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Speeches, 1978, undated (Folder 1: 11)
    Statements on issues
  - Subject file (Folder 1-2)
    - Advertisements, circa 1978 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Analysis of the vote, 1978 (Folder 1: 13)
    - Atlantic Richfield Company (ARCO), 1977 (Folder 1: 14)
    - California politics, 1972-1978, undated (Folder 1: 15)
    - Contributors, 1978-1979, undated (Folder 1: 16)
    - Election laws, 1974-1978 (Folder 1: 17)
    - Finance Committee, 1974-1978, undated (Folder 2: 1)
    - Fundraising, 1977-1978 (Folder 2: 2)
      Includes MacBride for President materials
    - Gay rights, 1977-1978 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Organization of campaign, 1977-1981 (Folder 2: 4)
      Includes statements and campaign proposal
    - Political Strategy Committee, 1977 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Proposition 13, 1977, undated (Folder 2: 6)
- United States presidential campaign of 1980 file, 1975-1982 (Box 2-10)
  Includes correspondence, clippings, speeches, press releases, campaign literature, scrapbooks, and files of Alicia Clark related to Clark's campaign for president of the United States as the Libertarian candidate. Arranged alphabetically by format.
  - Alicia Clark file (Folder 2-3)
    - General, 1980, undated (Folder 2: 7)
    - Biographical summary, undated (Folder 2: 8)
    - Campaign literature and drafts in Spanish, 1980, undated (Folder 2: 9)
    - Certificate, 1980 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Clippings, 1980-1981 (Folder 2: 11)
    - Correspondence, 1980 (Folder 2: 12)
    - Itineraries and calendar, 1980 (Folder 2: 13)
    - Press releases, 1980, undated (Folder 3: 1)
  - Ballot status report (map), undated (Folder 3: 2)
  - Biographical summary of Clark, undated (Folder 3: 3)
  - Briefings, 1980 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Campaign book A New Beginning by Ed Clark, 1980 (Folder 3: 5)
    Includes introduction by Eugene McCarthy
  - Campaign critique by David Nolan, 1980 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Campaign literature, undated (Folder 3: 7)
  - Clippings, 1979-1981 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Clippings scrapbooks (Folder 3-7)
    - September-December 1979 (Folder 3: 9-11)
    - December 1979-January 1980 (Folder 3: 12)
    - February-March 1980 (Folder 4: 1-2)
    - April 1980 (Folder 4: 3)
    - April-May 1980 (Folder 4: 4)
    - May-June 1980 (Folder 4: 5)
    - July 1980 (Folder 4: 6)
    - July 1980 (Contd.) (Folder 5: 1)
    - August 1980 (Folder 5: 2)
    - August-September 1980 (Folder 5: 3-4)
    - September-October 1980 (Folder 5: 5)
    - September-October 1980 (Contd.) (Folder 6: 1)
    - October 1980 (Folder 6: 2-4)
    - November 1980 (Folder 6: 5)
    - November-December 1980 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Correspondence (Folder 7)
    - General, 1979-1981 (Folder 7: 1-2)
      Includes letters to or from Edward Crane, Milton Friedman, Eric O'Keefe, Roger MacBride, and Murray Rothbard
    - Nolan, David, 1978-1980 (Folder 7: 3)
  - Declarations of candidacy for Clark and Koch, 1980 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Financial documents, 1979-1981 (Folder 7: 5)
    Includes balance sheets
  - Invitations to Clark, 1980 (Folder 7: 6)
  - Interview of Ed Clark by Bob Clark and James Wooten, 1980 (Folder 7: 7)
  - Interview of Ed Clark for Update, typescript, undated (Folder 7: 8)
  - Letterhead, undated (Folder 7: 9)
  - Memoranda, 1980 (Folder 7: 10)
  - Miscellany, 1980, undated (Folder 7: 11)
  - Newsletters, 1980 (Folder 7: 12)
    Internal campaign newsletter The Insider
  - Notes, undated (Folder 7: 13)
  - Press kit, 1980 (Folder 7: 14)
    Includes annotated speeches and notes
  - Press releases, 1980 (Folder 7: 15)
    Includes statements of Clark
  - Printed matter, 1975-1981 (Folder 7: 16)
  - Photographs, 1979-1980, undated (Folder 8: 1-3)
    Includes images of Clark campaigning, the KYW-TV studio in Philadelphia, a portrait of Clark, and a photograph from Al [Weiney]
  - Research and statistics on issues, 1980 (Folder 8: 4)
  - Reports (Folder 8)
    - "Marketing and Promotional Strategy for the Libertarian Party in 1980" by David Nolan (Folder 8: 5)
    - "Public Attitudes Toward Current Political Issues" study by Opinion Research Corporation, 1980 (Folder 8: 6-8)
      Includes public attitudes survey
  - Scrapbooks (Folder 8-9)
    - 1979 (Folder 8: 9)
    - 1979 (Contd.) (Folder 9: 1)
    - 1979-1981 (Folder 9: 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Folder 9: 3-4)
  - Speaking engagements and events file (Folder 9)
    - Flyers and programs, 1980, undated (Folder 9: 5)
    - Invitations, undated (Folder 9: 6)
    - Itineraries, 1980 (Folder 9: 7)
    - Press releases, 1980, undated (Folder 9: 8)
  - Speeches (Folder 9-10)
    See also press releases and press kit
    - "Acceptance Speech,", 1979 (Folder 9: 9)
      Clark's speech accepting presidential nomination at the Libertarian Party presidential convention
    - "Banquet Speech,", circa 1979 (Folder 9: 10)
    - "New Jersey Statement,", 1980 (Folder 9: 11)
    - "Speech #1,", undated (Folder 9: 12)
    - "Speech #2 (Business),", undated (Folder 9: 13)
    - "Speech #3 (Liberals),", undated (Folder 9: 14)
    - Speech about Reagan Administration, circa 1981 (Folder 9: 15)
    - Speech about education, undated (Folder 9: 16)
    - Speech given in Alaska, undated (Folder 9: 17)
    - Speech given in London, 1980 (Folder 9: 18)
    - Speech given in Los Angeles, undated (Folder 9: 19)
      Fragment
    - Speech outline, undated (Folder 10: 1)
    - "Statement of Ed Clark,", 1979 (Folder 10: 2)
    - Statement of Ed Clark given in Des Moines, 1979 (Folder 10: 3)
  - Subject file (Folder 10)
    - Bergland for Senate campaign, 1980 (Folder 10: 4)
    - Delegates to Libertarian Party conventions, 1978-1979 (Folder 10: 5-6)
    - Fundraising, 1980, undated (Folder 10: 7)
    - Media contacts, 1978-1982 (Folder 10: 8)
    - Television advertisements, undated (Folder 10: 9)
      Includes script
  - White papers, undated (Folder 10: 10)
- Libertarian Party file, 1972-1988 (Box 10-11)
  Includes materials related to the campaigns of Dan Dougherty and Gene Burns, correspondence of Alicia Clark, and Libertarian Party pamphlets.
  - Alicia Clark workshops, 1988 (Folder 10: 11)
  - Dan Dougherty campaign for governor, 1982, undated (Folder 10: 12)
  - Gene Burns presidential campaign, draft booklet, circa 1983 (Folder 10: 13)
  - Libertarian Party national convention, 1987 (Folder 11: 1)
    Includes correspondence of Alicia Clark
  - Libertarian Party pamphlets, undated (Folder 11: 2)
  - Libertarian Party platform, 1972 (Folder 11: 3)
  - Speakers Bureau manual, undated (Folder 11: 4)
- Audiovisual material, 1979-1994, undated (Box 11-13, film shelf)
  Includes video tapes, compact sound cassettes, sound disc, and motion picture film. Includes sound recording of Clark's acceptance speech at the Libertarian Party convention after being nominated as the presidential candidate. Descriptions are transcribed from labels on media; accuracy may vary.
  - Video and film (Folder 11-12)
    - Betamax tapes (Folder 11)
      - "Clark and Issues. Clark and News. Good Morning AM, Sun. Morning, Jim Berns,", undated (Folder 11: 5)
      - "Jim Berns, Barishni Kov, and Ed Clark. CBS News,", undated (Folder 11: 6)
      - "Jim Berns,", undated (Folder 11: 7)
    - 16mm motion picture film
      - "Clark for President,", undated
    - U-matic video tape (Folder 12)
      - "Project Flex, Ed Clark for President,", 1994 (Folder 12)
    - Two-inch video reels (Folder 12)
      - Reel from the American Broadcasting Company, undated (Folder 12)
      - Reel #2, Ed Clark, undated (Folder 12)
  - Sound recordings (Folder 12-13)
    - 45 RPM sound disc (Folder 12)
      - "Cane Creek Song. Blackberry Brambles," with Phil Busby and Steve Gronback, 1979 (Folder 12)
    - Compact sound cassettes (Folder 13)
      - Alicia Clark. Children's songs and games in Spanish, undated (Folder 13)
      - Bill Hunscher presidential nominee campaign speech at the Libertarian Party convention, 1979 (Folder 13)
      - "Ed Clark. 1988: What Was Accomplished & Learned," California/Nevada Libertarian Party, Las Vegas, 1989 (Folder 13)
      - Ed Clark acceptance speech at the Libertarian Party convention, 1979 (Folder 13)
      - "Ed Clark Acceptance Speech. Libertarian Party National Convention,", 8 September 1979 (Folder 13)
      - "Ed Clark Address to Commonwealth Club in San Francisco,", 1981 (Folder 13)
      - "Ed Clark, LBT, KOY,", 3 August 1979 (Folder 13)
      - "For President Vote Clark. Ed Clark Is the Man. Craig Franklin Is the Man,", 29 July 1980 (Folder 13)
      - "ISI Interview. Portland, Oregon,", undated (Folder 13)
      - "Libertarian Spots,", undated (Folder 13)
        Includes note from Craig Franklin
      - Radio show in Dallas, Texas, 30 July 1980 (Folder 13)
      - "Vote Clark,", undated (Folder 13)